Guide to the Henry Rushton Fairclough Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Henry Rushton Fairclough papers
1886-1937
SC0021
Fairclough, Henry Rushton, 1862-1938.
2 Linear feet
Correspondence with family and associates including Melville Best Anderson, John Casper Branner, Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover, David Starr Jordan, Chester H. Rowell, Benjamin Ide Wheeler, and Ray Lyman Wilbur. Also includes diaries, notes, photographs, newsclippings, pamphlets, published works, medals, and memorabilia.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Henry R. Fairclough, 1964.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Henry Rushton Fairclough was born near Barrie, Ontairo, Canada on July 15, 1862. He graduated from the University of Toronto in 1883. He also received his M.A., Litt. D. from there. From Johns Hopkins he received his Ph. D. in 1896. He was a fellow in Classics (1883-84) and lecturer in Greek (1887-93) at University College, Toronto. He came to Stanford in 1893 as assoc. prof. in Classics, teaching Latin, then Greek and Classical Literature. He became professor emeritus in 1917.
He taught at numerous universities at their summer sessions, such as the University of California, and Harvard. In 1910-11 he taught at American School at Rome, Italy. He also lectured on Archaeology.
In 1918-19, he was with the American Red Gross relief work in berne, Switzetland, then to Montenegro in 1919-20 where he was decorated with the Serbian Red Gross, and also siven the Serbian Order of White Eagle, etc.
He wrote books on the classics and also in collaboration others, translated several of Virgil, Plantus etc. He became editor of Student's Series Latin Classics, editor of Art and Archaeology (1925), editor of complete works of Virgil, and the Andrea of Terence in 1901. He died in Palo Alto, California on February 12, 1938.
Organizations which Fairclough Supported:
1. Classical Assoc. of Atlantic States
2. Archaeological Institute of America
3. Authors' Club
4. School of American Archaeology
5. American Philogical Assoc.
6. League of Nations Assoc.
7. California Nen of Prominence, Ltd.
8. Peninsula Arts Assoc.
9. Society for Promotion of Hellenic Studies
10. A.R.A. Assoc.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence with family and associates including Melville Best Anderson, John Casper Branner, Herbert and Lou Henry Hoover, David Starr Jordan, Chester H. Rowell, Benjamin Ide Wheeler, and Ray Lyman Wilbur. Also includes diaries, notes, photographs, newsclippings, pamphlets, published works, medals, and memorabilia.
Access Terms
Anderson, Melville Best, 1851-1933; Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922.; Fairclough, Henry Rushton, 1862-1938.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Rowell, Chester H.; Stanford University. Department of Classics. Faculty.; Wheeler, Benjamin Ide, 1854-1927.; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Diaries.; Pamphlets; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - A, 1900-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B, 1896-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - C, 1886-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D, 190d-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - E, 1896-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - F, 1897-1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Family corresp. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - G, 1895-1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - H; from Herbert C. Hoover (2), from Lou Henry Hoover (4), 1904-1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - I, 1915-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - J; from David Starr Jordan (19), 1893-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - K, 1894-1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - L, 1892-1737 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - M, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - N, 1895-1937 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - O, 1893-1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - P, 1893-1937 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - R; from Chester H. Rowell (2), 1899-1937 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - S, 1895-1931 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - T, 1905-1936 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - V, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - W, 1892-1937 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Z, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Unknown (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Outgoing Correspondence from Henry Rushton Fairclough, 1906-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - diaries and notes (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - photographs (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - clippings and pamphlets and misc. records (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - published copies of articles by Fairclough (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - published copies of articles by Fairclough and typescrif (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - published copies of articles by Fairclough (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - memorabilia--clippings etc. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - bibliographical material (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The Mediterraen Area typescript (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - David Brained Spooner", misc. holograph notes, records of Archaeological Institute of America (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - syllabus of course Greek 5 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - letters to Ers. Fairclough (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - five medals, silver match box with memorial coins inside (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - The Adelphoe of Terrence (The students series of Latin classics under the editorial supervision of Henry Rushton Fairclough), 1923 edition of 1896 publication (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - The Antigone of Sophocles translated by H.R. Fairclough and A. T. Hurray (Box 4)
  - Warming Both Hands by H. R. Fairclough typescript with holograph corrections (Box 4)
  - Warming Both Hands published edition (Box 4)
  - The Students' Series of Latin Classics--Virgil's Aeneid by H.R. Fairclough and S.L. Brown (Box 4)
  - The Classics and Our Twentieth Century Poets published address by H.R. Fairclough (Box 4)